Guide to the Jesusa Rodríguez Papers TAM.592
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jesusa Rodríguez Papers
1977-2024
1983-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rodríguez, Jesusa
Taylor, Diana, 1950-
TAM.592
9.75 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons, 3 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, 1 oversize folder, and 1 oversize backdrop
9.98 Gigabytes in 33 computer files
Laura María de Jesús Rodríguez Ramírez, known as Jesusa Rodríguez (born 1955 in Mexico City) is a director, actress, playwright, performance artist, scenographer, social activist, and senator (Moreno Party) in Mexico's Congress. She and her partner, Argentine singer/actress Liliana Felipe, operated El Hábito and Teatro de la Capilla, alternative performances spaces in the Coyoacán municipality of Mexico City, until 2005. In the 1980s Rodríguez notably directed an adaption of Mozart's Don Giovanni, featuring an all-female cast, entitled Donna Giovanni, and Oskar Panizza's El Concilio de Amor. Rodríguez won an Obie for Best Actor in Las Horas de Belén, A Book of Hours (1999) along with Ruth Maleczech and Mabou Mines. Rodríguez also contributes regularly to Mexico's most important feminist journal, Debate Feminista. This collection contains scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, magazines, photographs, contact sheets, programs and other ephemera, certificates, ID cards, diagrams, drafts and revisions of scripts, sketches, notes, sheet music, financial budgets, and correspondence from between 1977-2011 related to the creation and development of Jesusa Rodríguez's works as a director, playwright, and performance artist. The collection also contains materials relating to her work as a political and social activist, as documented by flyers, handouts, printed PowerPoint slides, articles, and optical discs containing video regarding gobierno legítimo de México, Creativa Resistencia, and the empowerment workshops that Rodríguez conducted. There are also empowerment workshop materials and participant letters.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Jesusa Rodríguez in 2011. The accession number associated with this collection is 2011.122. In October 2022, an accretion of materials previously held at the NYU Hemispheric Institute was transferred to the Tamiment collections; the accession number associated with this addition is 2022.083. In November 2024, Rodríguez transferred the costume of Coatlicue, which had previously been housed at the Hemispheric Institute; the accession number associated with this addition is 2024.064.
Appraisal
Extensive duplicates of handouts from the Activism series were discarded, with 3 copies retained.
Arrangement
The Jesusa Rodríguez Papers are arranged in four series:
Series I. Theater
Series II. Publications
Series III. Activism
Series IV. 2022 Accretion
Biographical Note
Laura María de Jesús Rodríguez Ramírez, known as Jesusa Rodríguez (born 1955 in Mexico City) is a director, actress, playwright, performance artist, scenographer, social activist, and senator (Moreno Party) in Mexico's Congress.
Well-known for her espectáculos, she steeped her performances in social and political commentary, and brought art into her activism. Although she is best known for her cabaret and political works, she has directed adaptations of diverse pieces, from William Shakespeare to Marguerite Yourcenar, opera to pastorelas.
Rodríguez studied at Centro Universitario de Teatro in Mexico City, and studied under director Julio Castillo, with whom she worked on several productions as a set designer, including Arde Pinocho. Early in her career she met her wife, Argentine singer and actress Liliana Felipe. They opened their first cabaret together, El Fracaso, and formed the theater group Divas A.C. with other actresses and playwrights. Divas A.C. would collaborate on many significant productions, including ¿Y cómo va la noche, Macbeth?, Trece señoritas: homenaje a Frida Kahlo, and most notably, Donna Giovanni.
An adaptation of Mozart's Don Giovanni, Donna Giovanni featured an all-female cast and toured across Europe. In 1988, Jesusa directed and starred in Oskar Panizza's El Concilio de Amor, which was also presented in several European countries and North America. In 1998, she first presented Las Horas de Belén in Mexico City, before staging the work Off-Broadway alongside Ruth Maleczech and Mabou Mines.
Jesusa Rodríguez first opened the performance space El Fracaso before opening and running the famous Teatro Bar El Hábito with her wife, Liliana Felipe. They ran El Hábito from 1990 to 2005, and over this span of 15 years, transformed their alternative performance space into a symbol of Mexican independent theater. Jesusa directed and staged hundreds of shows at El Hábito with numerous artists. In 2005, El Hábito was passed on to another cabaret group, Las Reinas Chulas, who changed the venue's name to El Vicio.
Alongside Liliana Felipe and fellow performer Regina Orozco, Jesusa Rodríguez had also done extensive work with indigenous communities throughout Mexico. Between 2001 and 2004, they ran workshops on empowerment, sex education, and re-articulating Mexican masculinity. Their workshops incorporated their theater experience, and they ran twenty-one of these workshops for indigenous and peasant women and men across 18 states of Mexico.
Jesusa's work as a performance artist informs her political and social activism, blending performance and protest into creative or artistic activism. She was involved in protests against substituting native corn for transgenic corn and the purchase of Monsanto by Bayer. She was also a part of the peaceful resistance movement and headed Resistencia Creativa, a movement that used "massive cabaret" as a political action tool. The movement was purportedly born in El Hábito, out of Mexico's highly contested 2006 general election and the political polarization and crisis that followed. With the election of conservative ruling party candidate Felipe Calderón by a fraction of a percentage, presidential candidate Andrés Manuel López Obrador immediately challenged the legitimacy of the election and its results. López Obrador and his supporters, including Resistencia Creativa, led mass protests, marches, and acts of civil disobedience, which culminated in a massive rally in Mexico City's historic Zócalo on July 30, 2006.
When then-senator Olga Sanchez Cordero became Secretary of the Interior in 2018, Rodríguez took Cordero's seat in the Senate. She is the first openly gay senator in Mexico.
Rodríguez also contributes regularly to Mexico's most important feminist journal, Debate Feminista.
Scope and Contents
The Jesusa Rodríguez Papers documents the development and process of significant theatrical productions in Jesusa Rodríguez's career as a theater director and performance artist, as well as the publicity and press related to this work. Some of the works prominently documented are Donna Giovanni and El Concilio de Amor. Additional works also featured in the collection are Ambrosio o La Fábula del Mal Amor, Las Horas de Belén, Atracciones Fénix, Pastorela Extraterrestre, and Così Fan Tutte. A large portion of the collection also documents the productions and events of the alternative performance spaces that she and her partner, Liliana Felipe owned and operated, El Fracaso and El Hábito. A large portion of the collection, particularly productions staged between 1983-1994, consists of scrapbook binders containing press clippings, photographic prints, contact sheets, negatives, theater programs, promotional materials, and other ephemera. Other materials documenting her theatrical productions include a curtain backdrop for Donna Giovanni, correspondence, magazines, newspapers, scripts and notes, drafts of lyrics, sheet music, articles, printed images, photographs, flyer layouts, brochures, financial documents, promotional mailers, fellowship proposals and applications, CDs and DVDs containing audio, video, and data, festival programs, certificates, identification cards, invitations, scene sketches and other drawings, painted illustrations, set designs and blueprints, and a calendar. As a social activist, Jesusa was involved in the protests surrounding the 2006 election, the peaceful civil resistance movement, and the anti-transgenic corn (En defensa del maíz) movement. For several years in the early 2000s, she ran empowerment workshops for indigenous and peasant women in Mexico. These activities are documented with press clippings, workshop materials and letters from workshop participants, flyers, handouts, printed PowerPoint slides, articles, and CDs and DVDs containing video and data.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Coatlicue is not to be a subject of interaction or engagement by researchers in reading rooms or classroom spaces. Photographs and videos of Coatlicue taken by NYU are to be available for study, research, and limited public exhibition.
Women performance artists; Women in the theater; Women theatrical managers; Women theatrical producers and directors; Women dramatists; Feminist theater; Theater programs.; Lesbian theater; Experimental theater; Scripts (documents); Drafts (documents); Photographs.; Negatives (photographs); Props (object genres); Theater -- Mexico; Dramatists, Mexican; Transgenic plants; Protest movements.; Elections -- Corrupt practices -- Mexico; Elections -- Mexico; Theatrical managers; Theatrical producers and directors.; Dramatists; Rodríguez, Jesusa; Taylor, Diana, 1950-; Felipe, Liliana
- Series I. Theater, 1977-2024, bulk 1983-2009; 1983-2009; 6.05 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 3 folder, and 1 oversize backdrop.; 6.78 Gigabytes on 4 optical discs.
  Arrangement
  Productions have been grouped together and arranged in chronological order. Following this are groupings of materials related to Jesusa and Liliana's performance spaces, fellowship materials, festivals, Liliana Felipe, collaborations between Jesusa and Liliana, and miscellaneous productions, also arranged in chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes materials documenting productions, performance spaces, fellowship materials, festivals, Liliana Felipe's work, and collaborations between Jesusa and Liliana. Some major productions that are documented are Donna Giovanni and El Concilio de Amor, and additional works, such as Ambrosio o La Fábula del Mal Amor, Las Horas de Belén, and Così Fan Tutte. A large portion of the collection, particularly productions staged between 1980-1994, consists of scrapbook binders containing press clippings, photographic prints, contact sheets, negatives, theater programs, promotional materials, and other ephemera. Some of thes binders originally labeled "misc." contain a variety of productions, including Coatlicue, and one of her earlier productions, Arde Pinocho, the latter of which she worked as a set and costume designer for director Julio Castillo. Other materials documenting Jesusa Rodríguez's theatrical productions include a curtain backdrop for Donna Giovanni, correspondence, magazines, newspapers, scripts and notes, drafts of lyrics, sheet music, articles, printed images, photographs, flyer layouts, brochures, financial documents, promotional mailers, fellowship proposals and applications, festival programs, certificates, identification cards, invitations, scene sketches and other drawings, a couple painted illustrations, set designs and blueprints, a calendar, and optical discs containing audio, video, and data (photographs). This series also includes digital photographs taken by New York University Libraries staff of the costume of Coatlicue prior to its physical acquisition.
  - Don Giovanni, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Don Giovanni 1 (1 of 2), 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Don Giovanni 1 (2 of 2), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Don Giovanni 2 (1 of 2), 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Don Giovanni 2 (2 of 2), 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Donna Giovanni 3 (1 of 2), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Donna Giovanni 3 (2 of 2), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Donna Giovanni 4 (1 of 2), 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Donna Giovanni 4 (2 of 2), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Donna Giovanni 1 (1 of 2), 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Donna Giovanni 1 (2 of 2), 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Donna Giovanni 2 (1 of 2), 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Donna Giovanni 2 (2 of 2), 1985-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Donna Giovanni, Borrowing Puppets, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ambrosio o La Fábula del Mal Amor (1 of 2), 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ambrosio o La Fábula del Mal Amor (2 of 2), 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - El Concilio de Amor, circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - El Concilio de Amor, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - El Concilio de Amor, 1989, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - El Concilio de Amor (1 of 2), 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - El Concilio de Amor (2 of 2), 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - El Concilio de Amor, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - El Concilio de Amor, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - El Concilio de Amor, 1987 and 1995 Adaptations with Alternative Endings, circa 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - El Concilio de Amor, 1988, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous El Concilio de Amor, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cielo de Abajo (1 of 3), 1992-1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cielo de Abajo (2 of 3), 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cielo de Abajo (3 of 3), 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Short Skits for Cabaret, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Atracciones Fénix, 1986, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Berlin en Luz, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Performance Celebrating Teresa and Ana María Pecanins, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Salinas Skits (1 of 2), 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Salinas Skits (2 of 2), 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Guru Barbie and Luminarias de la Sombra, circa 1995-2005 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Così Fan Tutte, circa 1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Las Horas de Belén, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Macbeth, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Pastorela Extraterrestre, 2002
    - Paper (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_592_ER_2
  - Enemigos de Fox, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Cabaret Prehispánico, 2004
    - Paper (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_592_ER_3
  - Noches de Bohemia, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Los Burrones, 2005-2006
    - Paper (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_592_ER_5
  - Aniversario de Benito Juárez en Coyoacán, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Noches Árabes al Pastor, 2006-2007 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Noches Árabes al Pastor, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - El libro de sexo gratuito, 2008-2009 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Diálogos entre Darwin y Dios, 2008-2009 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Presentación del libro, "La Ciencia como Calamidad" de Marcelino Sereigido en Guadalajara, circa 2009 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sor Juana en Almoloya and Primero Sueño de Sor Juana Inés de La Cruz, 2009-2011 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Guggenheim Fellowship, 1990-1997 (bulk 1990-1991) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Proposal, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hemispheric Institute of Performance and Politics, Encuentros, 2001-2005 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Festival Iberoamericano de Teatro de Bogotá, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - I.D.s, 1978, 1982, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Jesusa y Liliana, 1994, 2006-2007 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Liliana (1 of 2), 1980-2010 (bulk 2001-2010) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Liliana (2 of 2), 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Multiple Productions (1 of 3), 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Multiple Productions (2 of 3), 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Multiple Productions (3 of 3), 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Multiple Productions (1 of 2), 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Multiple Productions (2 of 2), 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Multiple Productions (1 of 2), 1997-2001 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Multiple Productions (2 of 2), 1995-2001 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Multiple Productions, circa 1985-1995, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Multiple Productions (1 of 3), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Multiple Productions (2 of 3), 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Multiple Productions (3 of 3), 1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Multiple Productions (1 of 2), 2001-2004 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Multiple Productions (2 of 2), 2002 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Texts, 1994-2002 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - El Fracaso (1 of 2), 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - El Fracaso (2 of 2), 1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Coatlicue, circa 1990-2024; cuid43290
    Coatlicue is a costume representative of the Aztec diety embodied by Jesusa Rodríguez, primarily in the performance piece "La gira mamal de la Coatlicue." Through her performance, Rodríguez transforms the statue of the goddess located at the Museum of Anthropology in Mexico City into a living entity. Rodríguez describes the performance as "pre-Hispanic cabaret," and through her embodiment of an Indigenous female entity parodies the attitudes of many Mexican politicians regarding challenges facing the country.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Coatlicue is not to be a subject of interaction or engagement by researchers in reading rooms or classroom spaces. Photographs and videos of Coatlicue taken by NYU are to be available for study, research, and limited public exhibition.
  - El Hábito (1 of 2), 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - El Hábito (2 of 2), 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - El Hábito (1 of 2), 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - El Hábito (2 of 2), 1992-1995 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - El Hábito (1 of 2), 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - El Hábito (2 of 2), 1991-1995 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Department of Labor Issues Against El Hábito, 2002-2006 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Last Day of El Hábito, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - La Capilla, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Donna Giovanni Curtain Backdrop, Undated; cuid906; 1 item one backdrop (Item TAM.592.cuid906)
- Series II. Publications, 1978-2009, bulk 1991-2009; 1991-2009; 0.7 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 1 oversize folder.
  This series is arranged in chronological order.
  The majority of materials in this series are whole magazines and other news publications, with a few press clippings intermixed. The articles are either reviews of productions or features on Jesusa Rodríguez.
  - Press, 1978-2007 (bulk 1991-1997) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Press, 1981-2004 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Press, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Press, 1999, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Papel Periódico y Fotos Entrevistas, 1999, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Press, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Press, 2002-2009 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Press, 2004-2009 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Press, 1986, 2009 (Box Shared Tamiment 054, Folder 2)
- Series III. Activism, 1990-2010; 0.5 Linear Feet in 1 record carton.; 14.8 Gigabytes on 4 optical discs.
  Folders have been arranged generally by subject/cause.
  This series contains press clippings related to various causes and protests that Jesusa Rodríguez was involved in, as well as flyers, handouts, printed PowerPoint slides, articles, and optical discs containing video regarding gobierno legítimo de México, Creativa Resistencia, and the empowerment workshops that Rodríguez conducted. There are also empowerment workshop materials and participant letters.
  - 2006 Election Activism, 1993-2006 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Oaxaca Graffiti Protests, 2006-2008 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Doña Jesusa Ramírez Gama, 1995-2007 (bulk 2000-2007) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Protest Articles, 1995-2009 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Protest Articles, 1990, 2000-2010 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Empowerment Workshops, 2001-2003
    - Paper (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_592_ER_1
  - Zapatistas, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - En Defensa del Maíz (1 of 4), 2004 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - En Defensa del Maíz (2 of 4), 2004 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - En Defensa del Maíz (3 of 4), 1996-2010 (bulk 2004-2007) (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - En Defensa del Maíz (4 of 4), 2010 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Protesta: Anti-violencia, Legalización de Marihuana, Maíz, 2007-2010
    - Paper (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_592_ER_4
- Series IV. 2022 Accretion, 1976-2019; 2.5 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 1 flat box
  This series has not been arranged by an archivist. Original order is unknown.
  This accretion to the Jesusa Rodríguez Papers consists of materials documenting Rodriguez's performances (including Hugostasás y Los Demás, El Rey Lear, and El Hábito) through photographs, reviews, scripts, set designs, programs, clippings, notes, ephemera, scrapbooks, and journals.
  - Catalog, 2019 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - El Hábito, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Announcement for Fashion and Art Show, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Journal, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Summerfare Festival, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Performance -- El Maíz, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Artwork, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Performance -- La Chinga, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Sketches, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Sketchpad, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - El Banquette, La Pantomime, Corrido de la Lamas, 1981-1991 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Hugotastás y los Demás, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Performance -- El Rey Lear, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Reviews, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Clippings and Ephemera, 1987-2010 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - El Hábito, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Stencils and Monographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Sin Maíz No Hay Vida (Chiapas), 2013 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Journal, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - El Partenon, El Erecto, y Los Ordenes, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - El Hábito Anniversary, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, circa 1980s-early 2000s (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
  - Photographs, circa 1980s-early 2000s (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Slides, circa late 1970s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - Comics, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Programs and Ephemera, 1980-2002 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1988-1991 (Box 8, Folder 7-10)
  - Set Designs, undated (Box 9, Folder 1-7)